<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book SYSTEM "docbook.dtd">

<book>
	<title>
		RapidBeans User Manual
		<author>
			<personname>Martin Blümel</personname>
		</author>
	</title>
	<preface>
		<para>
			Please note that this document is under construction!
		</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata format="GIF" fileref="RapidBeansUserManual-pictures/image001_underConstruction.gif"/>
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</preface>
	<chapter>
		<title>Goal of this project</title>
		<para>
			RapidBeans provides an easy to use environment to define a so called
			<phrase>domain model</phrase> which usually expresses the pure
			business logic of your application. The core idea of domain model
			centric development is that the domain model and the business logic
			implementation is the main part of your application.
			Other infrastructural parts of the application like UI
			(presentation layer) or persistence (datasource layer) should
			be handled by the framework as far as possible and require minimal
			implementation effort. The effort of evolution of this domain model
			should also be minimal. The infrastructure should adapt changes as good
			as possible. This includes as well evolving the UI as also the data shema
			- however data migration of course is an intrinsic problem.
		</para>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Key concepts</title>
		<para>
			The key concepts of the RapidBeans framework are:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>Simplicity:</emphasis>
						The KISS principle ("Keep it simple, stupid" or "Keep it simple and
						straightforward" are only two of many similar interpretations) is
						widely accepted. A similar principle is called "principle of least surprise"
						that means: do the things like most people would expect you to do them.
						However this goal is often hard to reach if you want to solve complex problems.
						The great art of information technology has always been to hide complexity and
						to let look complicated things simple and clear. It it as simple as that.
						Software that does not follow the KISS and the "least surprise" principle won't
						be maintainable and living in the long run.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>Document centricity:</emphasis>
						A Document is a bunch of structured, human and machine readable,
						self describing, more or less cohesive persistent data. A very simple
						and widely used approach is to store it into a single file.
						Document centric applications use documents not only to persist but
						also to exchange data.
						XML or JSON are widely accepted formats to store semantic (self describing)
						data that trade off human readability against machine readability.
						The RapidBeans framework currently provides an easy to use XML based
						approach to store an object graph into a file and to load it vice versa.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>RapidBeans FrameworkLayers</title>
		<section>
			<title>RapidBeans Core</title>
			<para>
				The RapidBeans core layer 
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>RapidBeans Datasource</title>
			<para>
				The RapidBeans datasource layer...
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>RapidBeans Presentation</title>
			<para></para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>RapidBeans Domain</title>
			<para>
				The RapidBeans Domain layer provides domain concepts
				beyond the very basic types from the core layer for usage
				in many domain models like DayOfWeek, Money, Length etc...
			</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>The RapidBeans modelling language</title>
				<para>
					The RapidBeans modelling language lets you describe an OO data model
					and type system similarly to an UML class diagram or Eclipse EMF Ecore
					in a very simple manner. Besides simplicity RapidBeans focuses on velocity.
					Therefore RapidBeans provides simple and flexible means of code generation
					but is also able to interpret the model immediately. You even are able to
					build a first simple application prototype out of the data model without
					generating one single line of code.
				</para>
				<section>
					<title>Types</title>
					<para>
						Basically you can use 3 different categories of types:
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para>beantype</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>enumtype</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para>quantitytype</para></listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</para>
					<section>
						<title>beantype</title>
						<para>Bean types a the core modelling unit describing complex
						datatypes equivalent to classes in the sense of OO.
						However while classes in the usual OO programming languages
						focus on describing attributes and operations, beantypes
						focus on describing attributes (called <emphasis>properties</emphasis>
						in this case) and their contraints (validations, businessrules).
						The second strenght is explicit modelling of associations.
						Operations are currently intentionally left out of the modelling
						language in order to keep it simple. However you probably will
						like to define some operations for your domain classes. In this
						case you can generate a Java class out of a bean type using the
						RapidBeans code generation facility and simply code your operations
						using Java methods.
						</para>
						<para>
						Example:
							<programlisting><![CDATA[<beantype name="org.me.addressbook.Person">
    <property name="lastname"/>
    <property name="firstname"/>
    <property name="dateofbirth" type="date"/>
    <property name="sex" type="choice"
        enum="Sex"
    />
    <property name="height" type="quantity"
        quantity="Length
    />
    <property name="groups" type="association"
        targettype="Group"
        inverse="persons"
    />
</beantype>]]></programlisting>
						</para>
					</section>
					<section>
						<title>enumtype</title>
						<para>The concept of enumeration types is widely known.
						Maybe their use for domain modelling sometimes is slightly underestimated.
						The RapidBeans enumeration types even are bit more powerful than enums
						as you might know them from C. You can also define a table of constant
						values together with such an enum (value table).
						Because since Java 5 enumeration types are also supported which have
						an idiom to support value tables the RapidBeans code generation facility
						perfectly maps them to Java.
						</para>
						<para>
							Example, simple enum:
							<programlisting><![CDATA[<enumtype name="org.me.addressbook.Sex">
    <enum name="male"/>
    <enum name="female"/>
</enumtype>]]></programlisting>
							Example, value table:
							<programlisting><![CDATA[<enumtype name="org.rapidbeans.domain.finance.Currency">
	<header>
		<column name="short2" type="String"/>
		<column name="short3" type="String"/>
	</header>
	<enum name="dollar">
		<cell name="short2" value="UD"/>
		<cell name="short3" value="USD"/>
	</enum>
	<enum name="euro">
		<cell name="short2" value="EU"/>
		<cell name="short3" value="EUR"/>
	</enum>
	<enum name="pound">
		<cell name="short2" value="LB"/>
		<cell name="short3" value="LIB"/>
	</enum>
</enumtype>]]></programlisting>
						</para>
					</section>
		<section>
				<title>quantitytype</title>
				<para>
					Quantity types lets you model physical quantities combining
					a magnitude a a unit. The type information for a quantity simply
					combines an enumeration of units with conversion factors.
					While the current implementation of quantity only provides
					BigDecimal as magnitude type (arbitrary precision) in the future
					quantities will support differnt magnitude number formats.
					</para>
					<para>
						Example, unit enum:
						<programlisting><![CDATA[<enumtype name="org.me.addressbook.UnitLength">
    <enum name="meter"/>
    <enum name="centimeter"/>
</enumtype>]]></programlisting>
						Example, quantitytype:
						<programlisting><![CDATA[<quantitytype name="org.me.addressbook.Length" 
    unitenum="UnitLength">
    <unit name="meter" factor="1"/>
    <unit name="centimeter" factor="/1E2"/>
</quantitytype>
]]></programlisting>
				</para>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Properties</title>
			<para>
				Properties are equivalent to attributes in the sense of OO but provide
				more than simple fields by allowing you to define constraints and
				associations is a declarative manner. This way you can easily implement
				a flexible and powerful domain value type system.
			</para>
			<table>
				<title>common property constraints</title>
				<tgroup cols="4">
					<colspec/>
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>constraint</entry>
							<entry>type</entry>
							<entry>default</entry>
							<entry>description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>mandatory</entry>
							<entry>boolean</entry>
							<entry>false</entry>
							<entry>null values not allowed</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>key</entry>
							<entry>boolean</entry>
							<entry>false</entry>
							<entry>input for property aware identity (keypropsstrict, keypropsloose)</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>readonly</entry>
							<entry>boolean</entry>
							<entry>false</entry>
							<entry>use for constants or derived properties (properties that may be only set by the program</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>transient</entry>
							<entry>boolean</entry>
							<entry>false</entry>
							<entry>property will not be persistet</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>final</entry>
							<entry>boolean</entry>
							<entry>false</entry>
							<entry>property will not be inherited</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
			<section>
				<title>string</title>
				<para>
					String simply stores a sequence of charecters limited only by the lenght of
					a single Java Straing. String is the default type for every property.
				</para>
				<table>
					<title>string property constraints</title>
					<tgroup cols="4">
						<colspec/>
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>constraint</entry>
								<entry>type</entry>
								<entry>default</entry>
								<entry>description</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>emptyvalid</entry>
								<entry>boolean</entry>
								<entry>false</entry>
								<entry>empty strings are valid or not</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>maxlen</entry>
								<entry>positive integer</entry>
								<entry>unlimited (-1)</entry>
								<entry>maximal string length</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>minlen</entry>
								<entry>positive integer</entry>
								<entry>0</entry>
								<entry>minimal string length</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>pattern</entry>
								<entry>Java regular expressions</entry>
								<entry>none (null)</entry>
								<entry>Defines a regular expression pattern to validate the string</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>multiline</entry>
								<entry>boolean</entry>
								<entry>false</entry>
								<entry>if multiple lines are possible or not</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>boolean</title>
				<para>
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>number: integer, decimal</title>
				<para>
				</para>
				<table>
					<title>number properties</title>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<colspec/>
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>property type</entry>
								<entry>encoding</entry>
								<entry>size / precision</entry>
								<entry>Java implementation</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>integer</entry>
								<entry>2nd complement / BCD</entry>
								<entry>byte01 / 8 bit, byte02 / 16 bit, byte04 / 32 bit, byte08 / 64 bit, unlimited</entry>
								<entry>byte, short, int, double, BigInteger</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>decimal (not yet impl.)</entry>
								<entry>floating point / BCD</entry>
								<entry>byte04 / 32 bit, byte08 / 64 bit, unlimited</entry>
								<entry>float, double, BigDecimal</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>choice</title>
				<para>
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>quantity</title>
				<para>
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>date</title>
				<para>
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>file</title>
				<para>
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>blob: clob, picture</title>
				<para>
					Not yet implemented
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>associationend: collection, map</title>
				<para>
				</para>
			</section>
		</section>
	</chapter>
</book>
